Guide to the Montana Military Veterans Oral History Project 1993-2002
Montana Historical Society Research Center
- ELMORE TINTZMAN INTERVIEW, OH 1957; 2 tape(s), Transcript 44 pages
  In this interview Elmore Tintzman discusses his decision to enlist for service during Korean War in the Navy; experiences traveling to Chicago for training; work and training in boiler room on various ships on Great Lakes and later along West coast; being shipped overseas aboard the U.S.S. Shelton; patrolling Korean shoreline; writing letters home to his wife; returning to the United States and being stationed in Long Beach; serving three tours in Korea; return to Montana; taking advantage of GI Bill to recieve agricultural training; receiving a veterans bonus; comparison of Korean and Vietnam Wars'; R and R in Hong Kong; and weather. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, September 6, 2001, Corvallis, MT
- CARL DRESCHER INTERVIEW, OH 1958; 1 tape(s), Transcript 14 pages
  In this interview Carl Drescher discusses his decision to enlist in the military as a Marine; his life in Anaconda or "Goose Town" as he calls it; service in Japan and China during World War II with 12th Marine Regiment, 3rd Marine Division; weather conditions during winter; living conditions including food and clothing; thoughts about Chinese soldiers; comparison of World War II, Korea and Vietnam Wars; thoughts about Douglas MacArthur; dealing with causalities; career in Marines following Korean War. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, August 17, 2001, Anaconda, MT
- WILLIAM C. JOHNSTON INTERVIEW, OH 1959; 1 tape(s), Transcript 23 pages
  In this interview William Johnson discusses his decision to join the Navy; serving three tours of duty in Korea; experiences with mined harbours; taking fire; work as a gunner's mate; service in Long Beach, California; training; life aboard ship; misfinformation about casualties and ships damaged that got home to his parents; returning home following discharge; buying first home with GI bill monies; and life following military service. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, August 28, 2001, Anaconda, MT.
- ROBERT N. PRIM INTERVIEW, OH 1960; 2 tape(s), Transcript 54 pages
  In this interview Robert Prim discusses working for the railroad in Livingston while he was still in high school; joining the Navy Reserve in 1950; being called to active duty; boot camp; training for radio operations; assignment to U.S.S. Merganser, a minesweeper; describes work of the minesweeper; life aboard ship including food, sleepingquarters; getting transferred to the Swallow; taking prisoners; issues of race aboard ship; wages received and hazardous duty pay; information received about on-shore fighting; experiences during R & R in Japan; return to the states to serve out his enlistment; attending school on GI bill following discharge; and returning to work for the rail road in Livingston as part of the Northern Pacific oil analysis department. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, September 25, 2001, Havre, MT
- DONALD R. ANDERSON INTERVIEW, OH 1961; 2 tape(s), Transcript 26 pages
  Donald R. Anderson discusses basic training in San Antone, Texas in 1947; the decision to enter the Air Force; specializing in aircraft welding; experiences on F-51 ground crew during Korean War; and returning home following service. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, October 3, 2001, Shelby, MT
- LOIS STAVES INTERVIEW, OH 1962; 1 tape(s), Transcript 26 pages
  Lois Staves, wife of Korean War Veteran and POW, discusses the birth of their first child; her husband leaving for his second tour of duty ten days later; his difficulties readjusting to civilian life following his first tour; impact of service on their marriage; her work for the telephone company in Missoula; taking classes at the University; her husband's restlessness following the war; reaction of community to returning Korean War Veterans; the role of the VFW in their lives; and her feelings about her son serving in the military, post September 11th terrorist attacks. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, September 28, 2001, Stevensville, MT
- RUDY CRAWFORD INTERVIEW, OH 1963; 2 tape(s), Transcript 54 pages
  Rudy Crawford discusses enlisting in the Army in 1947; basic training; service in occupied Japan; entry into Korean conflict in Pusan perimeter; being captured, questioned and released by North Korean soldiers; Chinese entry into the war; rotation out to Billings; work on burial crew in Missouri; contracting malaria; meeting and marrying his wife; and experiences boxing in the military. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, September 21, 2001, Billings, MT
- KENNETH D. HARVEY INTERVIEW, OH 1964; 2 tape(s), Transcript 38 pages
  Kenneth Harvey discusses his childhood and growing up in Harlem, Montana; enlisting in the Navy in 1950; basic training; military discipline; working on transport ships; participating in a mock invasion near Gwonchon; reenlisting in 1954; thought about Communism; thoughts about Vietnam War; and overall thoughts about his 30 year career in the military. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, September 20, 2001, Billings, MT
- KATHRYN STAUDINGER INTERVIEW, OH 1965; 1 tape(s), Transcript 28 pages
  In this interview Kathryn Staudinger discusses her childhood in North Dakota during the Depression; her family members military service during World War II; meeting and marriage to her husband William Staudinger; her huband's leaving for military duty in Korean War; being pregnant while husband in service; serviving on military dependents allotment; her family support system; communication problems; her husband's return; and overall impact of service on her family. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, September 2001, Laurel, Mont.
- ROBERT W. GRIMM INTERVIEW, OH 1966; 1 tape(s), Transcript 30 pages
  In this interview Robert W. Grimm discusses his enlistment in the Navy in 1951; military service of other family members; service in Japan; his work in military communications; encoding, radio and teletype; newspapers for soldiers; life on crusiers; returning to Montana and attending school in Bozeman; and life after military service. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, September 2001, Cut Bank, Mont.
- RALPH COX INTERVIEW, OH 1967; 1 tape(s), Transcript 30 pages
  In this interview Ralph Cox discusses growing up in Great Falls; joining the Navy Air Guard following World War II; special training received; running bombing flights; experiences during typhoon while stationed in Okinawa; his career in Navy following Korean War; running supply flights during Vietnam War; and his retirement in 1971. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, September 2001, Cut Bank, Mont.
- GERALD HOFFMAN INTERVIEW, OH 1968; 2 tape(s), Transcript 33 pages
  In this interview Gerald Hoffman discusses attending Northern Montana College studying industrial arts; being drafted into the Army to serve during Korea War; basic training; assignment to the Signal Corps; ocean trip to Korea aboard the Breckenridge; training regarding biological warfare; battlefield conditions; experiences in U.N. peace talks conference site; prisoner exchanges; returning to Montana following discharge; comparison of Korean War homecoming to World War II; using GI bill to continue education; his thoughts about communism in Korean War and Vietnam War era; and thoughts about terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, Billings, Mont., September 2001
- LESTER OELLERMAN INTERVIEW, OH 1969; 2 tape(s), Transcript 39 pages
  In this interview Lester Oellerman discusses his family history in the Glendive era; being drafted in 1950 into the Army; basic training; the difficulties of sea crossing to Japan; work as personnel specialist hauling a typewriter with him, even to the front lines; difficulties of troops lives; different reports he created; living conditions or orphans (mostly Korean-American children); thoughts on communism; thoughts about other nations troups, including England, France, Turkey; challenges of keeping records near the front lines; maintaining contact with family and fiancee; returning home following discharge; gaining work in Postal Service in Glendive; the U.S. Veterans Administration; and Chinese military propaganda. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, September 26, 2002, Glendive, Mont.